Hi, my name is Yo Yehudi. I'm
the open source technology lead
for the data science and health
team at the Wellcome Trust. And
I'm here today to talk a little
bit about what my team does to
actually fund foundational
tools, trust and talent for open
research in life science. And I
also have my twitter and
fediverse handles here. So if
you want to tweet or toot about
the talk, then you can do so.
And also some contact details at
the end of the slides as well,
including my email address. So
I'm going to start by setting a
scene.
First of all, let's talk about
Sam. So Sam is the scientist who
does science in the lab, wearing
a lab coat and perhaps doing
interesting things with
pippettes or microscopes. This
is possibly what the traditional
images that pops into people's
head when they think about the
word scientist, but it's really
only half the picture.
So this case, I will actually
also be talking about Joy. And
primarily, I'll be talking about
Joy. They work in the same area,
Sam, but they focus more on
computational research. And they
tend to write their code, do
their work, to tidy data, maybe
to analyse or visualise their
results. And it might even be
that they couldn't do their work
at all without code, because
maybe they have gigabytes and
gigabytes worth of image data or
some other type of big data that
really does need to be analysed
using computation.
Sometimes these types of data,
there's no way a single human or
even a team could properly
analyse it. And so we do have a
lot of computers in research.
And I suspect that since I'm
speaking to the open research
room at fosdem, many of you may
already be computational
researchers and be familiar with
this. But I think it's important
to set that baseline for
everyone else since this isn't
only an academic conference.
Anyway, code is a non
traditional research and
academic output, which means
that it doesn't really fit into
the same incentive systems that
may already exist within
research. So actually, all of it
both Sam and Joy's work is still
really important, and it's
around a stain definitely.
Today, we'll focus on joy. And
if you identify with Joy, then
hopefully this is a talk for
you. So I'll dig a little bit
into the title of my talk, which
was talking about the tools, the
talent and the incentive. So
what my some of the challenges
that actually people have today
is that we have missing
computational tools. For the
research, should we have
insufficient incentive to draw,
retain and reward talent, and
insufficient trust in
computational work.
Right. So first of all, looking
at tools, there's a couple of
interesting and perhaps almost
opposite cases here that may
occur. On the one hand, research
by its nature is often cutting
edge, or it's just such a very
narrow domain that actually the
software tools don't yet exist
for people need to do. On the
other hand, in some domains,
there's the opposite problem,
where actually the tools are
fragmented. And so there might
be lots and lots of different
standards and lots and lots of
different ways to do something.
Of course, here I have the
obligatory XKCD, talking about
how easy it is to actually
result in fragmented standards.
Anyway, these are two challenges
with regarding to tools I'm sure
there are many, many more. So
I'll also try and talk about
trust. So unfortunately, I think
a lot of us are familiar with
different ways that tech has
gained a bad name, and has
gained in many cases a bad name
for a good reason. For example,
anonymized data is very often
re-identifiable. It's not that
long ago, we heard about the
huge Cambridge Analytica
Facebook data scandal. And
perhaps most recently, people
have been flocking away from
WhatsApp due to privacy
concerns. I think the problem
around trust is that like I
mentioned earlier, computational
research for managing people's
data is really, really
essential. There's so many
scenarios where we can't do it
any way except computationally
do the work that we need to do,
because there's too much data or
it's too is too complex for us
to do it any other way. But at
the same time, if we haven't
acted in trustworthy ways, and
we haven't actually proven that
we deserve the trust of people,
then that people are going to be
understandably wary of sharing
data and of working with
computational tools, which means
it can be really hard to make
the necessary advances that we
actually want to help people
when we do have good intent.
And so I'll talk a little bit
more perhaps about talent as
well. So to set the scene or
perhaps elaborate a little bit
on how research and academia
works. So if you remember, Sam,
the traditional researcher, when
they finish up their lab work,
they'll write up what their
results are. And they'll publish
this paper that they've written
in a journal. And so since this
is this is how things evolved.
The academic credit model
typically revolves around how
many papers you've written, and
what's in those papers. But Joy
does certainly write papers,
Joy's the computational
researcher, so they spend time
writing code. And code isn't yet
built into the system in the
same way. So it's not measured
or incentivized. And ultimately,
if you're writing code, you're
probably not writing papers, and
you may not be earning the types
of research that might advance
your career prospects,
unfortunately.
And so while code produces
scientific outputs, it also
doesn't mean that people
actually appreciate good
practice. So I know as a
research software engineer, I
would appreciate it if I came
back to my own code, and I'd
done good documentation or you
know, written tests or done
whatever other good bit of
practice I should be doing. And
I know that any other
maintainers, who maybe stepped
up after me would also
appreciate that, but I'm not
sure if anyone else would. Right
now, unfortunately, this is
another thing that we really
don't incentivize, which kind of
actually nicely moves on to my
next point.
So another problem with code
related outputs is that they
might not be shared. And this
could be because there wasn't
good practice, like I mentioned
earlier, or it could be related
to other reasons. For example,
people may want to capitalise on
intellectual property or
something else. And, and perhaps
another interesting area is that
researchers may not always wish
to share, that they actually are
writing code. So this could be a
recall when I was at fosdem last
year, someone said that it was
incredibly hard to actually get
a grant to get someone to pay
you to write software.
And one of the consequences of
that is that you might not write
in your grant application that
you're even writing code,
because you may feel like you
need to obscure it just in order
to get funded. But we believe
that you should be able to say
that you want to write code,
because this is how this type of
work is done. And I'm going to
do this code well. So another
interesting thing is that some
people also don't even realise
that they're coders. I recall
having a chat one day with
someone and I explained that I
was a research software
engineer. And she said that that
was kind of interesting. But
also not something she had any
knowledge about. And then later
in that same conversation, she
mentioned that she actually uses
our every single day. So I'm
like, well, this is this is
code, and it's an important part
of science, you are a coder. But
of course, if she doesn't think
that she's doing code, then
she's probably not going to be
mentioning this in her grant
applications. And as a funder,
we don't necessarily get a
realistic picture of what's
going on if people aren't
actually feeling like they can
talk about code at all, as part
of science. So we really want
people to be able to open up and
share and tell us what they're
doing around code, so that we
can incentivize and reward it
and understand it a bit better.
Another problem in the talent
area is that we are in an
intersection of places where
diversity tends to be really
bad. GitHub survey in 2017 found
that over 90% of open source
contributors were men. And a
recent report from the software
Sustainability Institute in the
UK similarly found that 6% of UK
research software engineers
reported as disabled, and 5%
reported as black or minority
ethnicity were at the
intersection of so many of these
different places, which means
that we're probably not getting
the best quality outputs that we
could get, since we only have a
real small subset of people that
there actually are available
working on this and putting
their views into what's going
on.
I will also talk a little bit
about the Wellcome Trust
strategy. So sort of previously,
I've been talking about some of
the problems in the domain and
some of the things that I think
my team are really interested in
doing. But the Wellcome Trust is
a science funder largely. And
right now we've sort of shifted
our focus to look at really
three primary areas as well as
discovery research, which is a
bit broader, but we have a
really strong focus on global
heating on mental health and on
infectious disease.
And I will also give you some
examples, I've got a couple of
open source software projects
that we've actually just funded
really recently both of these
have been co funded with other
funding organisations or in this
case, afrimapr was co funded
with Wellcome's Open Research
team. And it is a Shiny/R-based
tool that actually allows you to
look up healthcare facility
locations in Africa is
integrated data both I think
from citizen science data as
well as governmental data
sources
Another open source project that
we've recently co funded is
OpenSAFELY, which allows people
to allows
that you can find maintenance
money for, for example, and that
you feel like you're justified
doing documentation for users
and software developers who want
their code to be accessible, we
want to make sure that... whilst
FAIR, FAIR is great, and this
time I'm also talking about
things like making sure that
your code works with screen
readers, if that's relevant, or
that there is captioning, for
example, if there is audio
content, and a huge, huge part
of open source. Success is
community. And, as I mentioned,
many of the people here and we
are an open source software
conference, people are aware
that very often putting your
code online isn't enough to make
people contribute. But actually,
you may want community managers
and people who spend a lot of
time thinking and working with
people to actually bring in
contributions. And this is an
important part of measuring the
sustainability of software as
well.
here's a couple of calls to
arms. And so if you, if this has
sort of spoken to you, and you
have some examples of things
that you would like to share,
please, please contact me my
email address is on the next
page, we are launching at the
minute a blog to spotlight good
practice in open source research
software.
is that we want to be funding
software tools. So if you think
you fit into life science
domains, either as a really
foundational software tool, or
one of the three specific areas
that I mentioned, that Wellcome
is focusing on - mental health
and infectious diseases and
global heating, then please,
please do contact me. So my
email address is here. And
there's also the whole team's
email address if you prefer
that.
But I'm also happy to sound off
ideas and just discuss things if
you think that there's something
that you're not sure what might
be a good fit, or if you need to
talk through a bit more before
spending time and effort
thinking about it. And with
that, I'll say thank you very
much and happy to take any
questions. Thank you